Hi everyone, in our previous
session, we got stopped at here.
In today's session, we will learn
something which is very important,
which are called static methods and
class methods.
So let's go to our resume tailor
agent code base, which I showed you
in the beginning.
So in this code base, if you look at
this one, there is a method here.
In this method, there is no self
here. There is no self.
But what did we learn in the
beginning?
Whenever there is a function inside
the class, then by default the first
parameter is self.
But here, it is not in this
function.
And there is something called as
static method.
So what is this? This is called
decorator.
We will learn more about this in
some time.
And maybe let's look at one more
method inside a class.
There is a class here called JD
analysis.
And inside this, if you look at
here, define normalized seniority.
Inside this, it is not self.
It is something called as CLS.
What is this?
And there is something called as at
the rate class method.
So what are these methods?
How is it different from the methods
that we write?
There is something like this.
It has self. It is similar to
underscore, underscore,
init, underscore, underscore.
What is the difference between all
these? How should this be used?
That is what we are going to learn
in this video, which are class
methods and static methods and
regular methods.
What is the difference between these
three? How should it be used?
This is our code base.
The day after tomorrow, your HR
manager will come and she will
request for three changes.
One is, I have a company -wide
percentage.
It is not 4%. I want to change it to
7%.
Okay.
And the second question is,
she wants to get the total number of
employees.
That is also fine.
And the third question is,
on any given day, let's say 2026
January 1st,
we have to find out whether it is a
working day or not.
So those are the three requests.
So with the existing code base that
we have, let's try to answer all of
these things.
What is our first question?
She wants to change the company
-wide percentage to 7%.
So what can I do?
I can write one more method.
In that method, I can say,
set raise percentage and it will
take a self parameter.
And how much amount should I send?
Maybe 1.07 or 7%.
By writing like this, do you think
it is an issue or not?
What did we use in the last part?
Whenever you put self,
what is self?
Self will always go to an instance.
So when you say self.raisePercentage
is equal to amount,
what are you doing here?
You are trying to change the raise
percentage of an employee.
But you are not doing the raise
percentage for the whole class
employee.
And if you don't understand why it
happens like that,
please watch my previous video which
covers the same exact situation on
Python OOPs part 2.
And if the self is only changing for
a particular instance of a class,
employee1 or employee2,
can't I just write employee
.raisePercentage
equal to amount?
Yes, you can absolutely do
this.
But the problem is,
you are directly hard coding this
employee.raisePercentage
inside a method which takes self as
a parameter.
If you want to change the raise
percentage of a particular employee,
how are you going to do that?
So it is not going to work and it is
not an ideal situation as well.
And you will learn more about why it
is not good in the next class,
which we will talk about class
inheritance.
And there is one more problem with
self parameter.
If I want to increase the raise
percentage,
I need to create an instance of this
employee
and after that I can put set
.raisePercentage.
What is my task?
I need to change the raise
percentage to the entire employee
class.
So why do I even need to create an
instance?
And only after creating this
instance,
I can call this function.
Without this instance,
I cannot call this function.
It will throw error because I don't
know what self is.
So why do I even need to call this
instance
to call this set.raisePercentage
amount?
It is fundamentally not good.
That is where you will learn more
about class methods.
And the second problem is,
now HR came and asked how many
employees are there in our company.
So how are you going to get that?
We already have a variable called
numberOfEmployees.
And in it we are increasing that
variable to plus 1.
Whenever you are calling a class,
you are increasing the employee
count.
That is fine.
If I want to retrieve that amount,
I can just create a function
like this,
getCount and self.numberOfEmployees.
What will happen if I do this?
The same problem again.
I need to have an instance to be
created
to call the employees.
What we are going to do is,
I want to find how many number of
employees do we have.
You can think that I can directly
call employee.getCount.
There is a method in this,
right?
But what will this method take?
It is taking self as a parameter.
So let's execute this and see what
is happening.
There is a method here.
Self is important for this method.
To call this method,
I need to create an employee.
Only after creating an employee,
I need to call this one.
Now let's see what happens.
I am creating an instance of an
employee class
with the variable employee1.
And then I am saying employee1
.getCount.
Now let's try to execute this
and see if we can get the output.
Look, we got the output as 1.
Why?
We created this employee instance in
this employee1.
And we call this employee1.getCount.
So what is the fundamental problem?
To see how many employees are there
in my company,
why do I need to create an employee?
That is bad, right?
Can't I directly just get the
employee count?
That is the second problem.
And the third problem is
what if HR wants to know
if a given day is a working day or
not?
What do you do for that?
I create one more function
which is called isWorkday.
It takes self.
And I am calculating
if our kitchen day is a working day
or a weekday.
So basically how it will work is
0 is coded as Monday
and 6 is coded as Sunday.
So Monday is 0, Tuesday is 1,
Wednesday is 2, Thursday is 3,
Friday is 4, Saturday is 5,
and then Sunday is 6.
So like this, whatever the number
that we get,
we will decide based on
whether that number is a weekday or
a weekend.
So why do we even need to have self?
What is the use of self?
So for such problems,
we have something called as
class methods and static methods.
These will solve all of these
problems for us.
And we will learn exactly
how to create class methods
and how to use static methods
to solve all of these problems.
So class method is a method
whose first parameter is
not self but class.
So if I want to create a method
for class method,
I need something called as a
decorator.
That decorator is
the @classmethod decorator.
So we are explicitly saying
or telling to Python
that this method should
be created for class method.
So what do I do?
When there is a class method,
it should not be self,
it should be something called as
CLS.
CLS means class.
Here imagine you are not
providing the instance of a class,
instead you are providing
the entire class itself.
Class is the complete keyword
we are using to define the class
itself.
That is why we are using
the CLS parameter.
It is also a keyword in Python.
And here instead of
self.raisePercentage,
we will put CLS.raisePercentage.
So now you can think
about this like
here you are passing the entire
class.
What have you done so far?
You are passing an instance
of a class, either employee1 or
employee2.
But we are not doing
that anymore and we will see
how it will affect the whole
employee class.
Now let us print
employee.raisePercentage.
How much is our initial percentage?
It is 1.04.
And now let us print this one.
Indentation error
but let us do like this.
Let us execute this code.
See 1.04.
So what have we done here?
Instead of us creating an instance,
you are directly accessing
this class variable.
That is also the first thing.
And the second thing is,
let us set the
employee.setPercentage to
1.07.
Now for the entire class,
we are changing this variable to
1.07 and let us print that
after this employee.raisePercentage.
And let us not do this for now.
And let us execute this.
And see, initially
it is 1.04.
That is fine. That is how we defined
initially when we created the class.
And after that, when we say
employee.setRaisePercentage
in this class method,
it is setting up the
class.raisePercentage.
What is our class here?
Employee.
Employee.raisePercentage
is changing this value from 1.04
to 1.07.
That is why when we
are printing this employee
.raisePercentage
again after setting up this value
to 1.07, we get
the value as output 1.07.
And it will affect
everywhere guys. Let us say
we will define two employees.
Employee1 and Employee2.
And after creating
employee1 and employee2,
we are setting employee
.setRaisePercentage
to 1.10. What is the meaning of
this?
For the two employees
we are setting the
global value class variable to
1.10 instead of 1.04.
So, let us print that
employee1.raisePercentage and
employee2.raisePercentage.
So, let us look at the
output. See, initially
there was 1.04.
Then we set it to 1.07.
After that we created two employees.
And then after that we made it to
1.10. And that is why
we are getting 1.10 and 1.10
here. So, this is why
when you want to set
something at a class variable
level, then always use
class methods. When you
use class methods, you do not need
any
self parameter. And that is what
we have seen here in this model.py.
We are creating a class method
and then you are taking the entire
class itself.
Hopefully it is clear.
And then the next example
we need to find the number of
employees.
Now we will convert this
into a class method.
Because number of employees is not
based on instance level.
I will say class method.
And inside
I need to take self.
And here class.number
of employees I want to return.
Now to execute this,
I can directly first call
what is the number of employees that
we have
directly using employee.
GetCount and
here I need to put class
cls. Yeah. Yeah. Cool.
So, employee.GetCount
Initially we do not have any
relevant employees.
And we will get the output as
0. After that we are creating
employee. Rahul and Sharma
and Rs. 8 lakhs. Employee
Priya, Patel and Rs. 9 lakhs.
Employee Amit Kumar and Rs.
7 lakhs.
And whenever you are creating
these employees, what are we doing
here?
We are increasing the count of this
number of employees.
So, what if at the end I want to get
the count of employees?
I can directly
do print employee.GetCount
Here I am not using
employee1.GetCount
and employee2.GetCount.
I am
calling it based on the complete
class level.
So, that is why
it is very important to define class
methods whenever you are working
with
the class variables. And one of the
common mistake is that many people
write code like this, but they don't
provide this class method.
This decorator
is very very important.
Now let's talk about static
method. What is there in our code?
There is a function called
isWorkday.
Now I have a date
2026518 and I want to
see if it is a working day or not.
If I want to use this function,
how should I call it?
First I need to create an employee
instance
and then I need to put
instance.isWorkday
and then it will take this date
and it will print whether it is a
work day or not.
If we think about it,
what is the need of
employee1 or self inside
this function? Can't I just
directly pass the day and get
my work day or not?
Absolutely!
That is the whole point of static
methods. If you don't need
self anywhere, then what is the
point
of creating self in the function?
So what you do is
you put something called
static methods. Look here
I got the output as true.
So how can I convert a normal
method into a static method?
Very simple. I will put here
at the rate
static method. So earlier we
put the class method as a decorator.
Static method will take the
decorator
as static method. And here
I will not have any
self or CLS or nothing at all.
It is just like pure Python
functions. And then
I can return what is my weekday.
If I want to call this static
method,
I don't need to
create an employee instance.
If I want to say it is a working day
or not,
why do I need to even create an
instance?
So I can directly
say import date time. From there
I am creating two different dates.
2024 415
and 2024 414.
One is Monday and one is Sunday.
And how can I call this static
method? I can directly say
employee which is my
class name. What
is my static method? Is workday
and you pass your date?
Simple. Nothing complex at all.
Look here. I got true and
false. That is what
static methods are for.
Whenever you don't have any
class or instance
for the operations in a method,
then that is the point where you
will
create static methods.
So to summarize, to build a normal
method,
you will just create a function
and in that first by default
parameter will take self.
And if you are accessing any of the
parameters inside this normal
method, then you need to access
using
self.name. And if you
want to build something called as
class
method, you will put the decorator
as class method. And here
instead of self, you will set a
parameter
called cls. And it will be
applicable
over the entire class.
Whenever you don't have any class or
instance
then that is the point where you
will create your static methods and
it will not even take cls or
self at all. Maybe I just wanted to
show you
one more example. Let's say
there is one more class.
Class is
called string helper and
it has two static methods.
It will convert
the words we pass into
snake case. And one more thing
if you pass something which contains
at the rate, to check whether it is
an email or not, it will check
whether
it is a valid email or not based on
if at the rate is present inside the
text
and if there is a dot or not.
These are
two methods which doesn't care
about class or instance.
So if I can execute these two,
see, hello world
is an input which is in caps lock
space. But we converted
that into hello underscore word
using the static method.
Let's say there is an email at the
rate b dot com
and I wanted to see if it is a valid
email or not. And by
passing to this function,
I can see it
is true. Now you might have a
question
in your brain. If it is acting just
like a normal function,
why should we
write it inside a class?
Why can't
I just directly write this outside?
That's a valid question.
Now how can I write this?
And even if I write like this
define is valid email
outside a class
and if I just call this one
is valid email, so let's
say print is valid
email at the rate b dot
com and if I print it
even this will give me
true. That is absolutely
correct. In short, static
methods are basically normal
Python functions which
are being built inside a class
because
if there is no class inside
people will tend to forget
that there is a function like this.
That is the whole sole
purpose. We are putting normal
functions inside a class such
that tomorrow if HR
is using this code, then she
can directly access employee
dot get count
employee dot is
workday, employee dot set raise
percentage.
So without floating functions
everything will be
bound to a single class
that's why we will use
static methods inside a class
whenever there is no need of a class
or instance to it. Now
what we are going to do is
let's put every single thing
together in a
single class. So let me
zoom in a little bit. So this is
the code. So import date time
or package import and we
created an employee class
in which I have class variables
raise percentage, number of employees
company enforces and
inside this I have my first
constructor
which is def underscore underscore
init underscore underscore
it takes self, first, last
and pay. First we will build two
regular methods, apply raise and full
name
in these two self is
mandatory because these are regular
methods
and whenever you are accessing some
variables
inside these regular methods you
need to put
self dot pay or self dot first,
self dot
last. And then next we will
create class methods. Whenever
you are creating class method
always use this decorator at the
right class
method. After that in the function
definition use this cls
parameter and inside the function
access this cls dot raise
percentage. And then we will
create one more class method and
then
static method. In static method
there is nothing
like class or self
it will just be like a pure python
function. Nothing fancy.
After that what we will do,
we will create
our instances and we will apply
raise
and we will print every single
thing. So
what is your homework,
I will put this
code in the github link below
go through this code and understand
output at every line. I have
given the output here but you
practice on your own whether you are
able
to get the output from your own
or not. So if you can
do that please let me know in the
comment section below.
So let's go back to our
final code. See
now we have class methods
we have something called as property
and we will
learn about remaining decorators
later on
but we can create normal
class. See class match
analysis we have
the class method and then property
and then we have the properties
and then class methods
and LLM client law we have the
static
methods as well. So this is how
you will write class methods and
static methods
inside the OOPs concept format
classes.